Guide to the Sir William Sidney Smith papers, 1794-1862 MS 267
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Sir William Sidney Smith papers
1794-1862
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Smith, W. Sidney (William Sidney), Sir, 1764-1840
MS 267
3 Linear Feet (1 box and map drawer)
The papers of Admiral Sir William Sidney Smith contain letters concerning Smith's brother, John Spencer Smith, who was British ambassador to the Porte at Constantinople in the early 1790s. Correspondents include Robert Liston, British Minister to the United States. Also included is a genealogy of the Smith family, a battle order issued by Smith aboard HMS Tigre during the siege at Acre in 1799, and an invitation to the funeral of the Duke of Wellington.
Biographical Note
Sir (William) Sidney Smith (1764–1840), naval officer, was born on 21 June 1764 in Park Lane, London, the second son of John Smith of Midgham, Berkshire, a captain in the guards and gentleman-usher to Queen Charlotte, wife of George III.
Smith entered the navy in 1777 and saw action in the American War at Cape St Vincent (16 January 1780) and off the Chesapeake (5 September 1781). In 1785–7 he studied French at Caen before spending a year with the Swedish navy. In 1793 he was posted to Toulon and returned with dispatches after its fall. Smith was given command of the frigate Diamond which he used to conduct partisan warfare along the French coast. He was captured in 1796 off Le Havre and imprisoned in the Temple, Paris. Two years later he escaped and returned to command the Tigre in Levant. The most famous episode in his career came in 1799 when he undertook the defence of Saint-Jean d'Acre (3 March–8 May) and heroically repulsed Napoleon. He died in Paris and was buried in Père-Lachaise.
Excerpted from:
JOHN CANNON "Smith, Sir Sidney." The Oxford Companion to British History. Encyclopedia.com. 8 Aug. 2021
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, watercolor sketches, printed documents document the career and family of Sir William Sidney Smith. The bulk of the letters concern Smith's brother, John Spencer Smith, who was British ambassador to the Porte at Constantinople in the early 1790s. Correspondents include Robert Liston, British Minister to the United States. Also included is a genealogy of the Smith family, a battle order issued by Smith aboard HMS Tigre during the siege at Acre in 1799, and an invitation to the funeral of the Duke of Wellington.
Access Restriction
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This material was purchased from manuscript dealers, 1956-1964.
Index Terms
Subjects
Military
Document Types
military records; corrrespondence; genealogies (histories)
Places
Great Britain
Subjects (Persons)
Liston, Robert, Sir, 1742-1836; Smith, John Spencer, 1769-1845
- Series I: Correspondence, 246441
  - Letters from Robert Liston to John Spencer Smith, 1794, 246454 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Robert Liston to John Spencer Smith, 1795-1796, 246453 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from W.S. Smith to Robert Liston, March 1796, 246452 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Charles Douglas Smith to General Edward Smith (genealogical information), 1801, 246451 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters - copy of manuscript contents of family Bible from Charles D. Smith to J.S. Smith, 1802, 246450 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter from Constance Smith to General Edward Smith, Dec. 11, 1804, 246449 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter unsigned from W.S.Smith, ca. 1805-1806, 246448 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2 autographed letters from W. S. Smith to Sir John Stuart, 1806, 246447 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter from C.D. Smith on genealogical information, April 12, 1809, 246446 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Autographed letter from W.S. Smith, June 27, 1821, 246445 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Autographed letter from W.S. Smith, Dec. 10, 1829, 246444 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Autographed letter from W.S. Smith to Lord Palmerston, July 22, 1836, 246443 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 2 letters from W.S. Smith, May 28, 1858, 1866, 246442 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: General and military records, 246431
  - French passport of W.S. Smith, May 28, 1799, 246440 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Printed notice to the freemen of the City of Rochester from W.S. Smith, May 12, 1802, 246439 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Orders signed from W. S. Smith to Captain Prowse, Dec. 5, 1806, 246438 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Appointments of J.S. Smith, 1774, 1807, 246437 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Commission of Edward Smith, Nov. 30, 1811, 246436 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Commission of Major Lionel Hook at Lt. Col. in the Army, Aug. 3, 1815, 246435 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Commissions of W. S. Smith II, 1823, 1827, 246434 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Times description of the Battle of Trafalgar, Nov. 7, 1805, 246433 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings and death notices, n.d., 246432 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series III: Family records, engravings, and watercolors, 246412
  - Engravings of Constance Smith and J.S. Smith, 1802, 246430 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook started by W.S. Smith II, 1862, 246429 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Genealogy of W.S. Smith II, part 2, maternal; Constance Catherine Sophia, Baroness Herbert [from scrapbook], 246428 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - George Sidney Smith [from scrapbook], 246427 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Family information and pictures [from scrapbook], 246426 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Family crest, n.d., 246425 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Watercolors [11], n.d., 246424 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "To Mr. Herbert Smith - hair of his uncle, W.S. Smith, cut off after his death; rec'd Caen July 1840", 246423 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 2 seals, family crest, 246422 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gold leaf framed brownstone sketch of Capt. W. Bligh, R.N., 246421 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Framed round engraving of Constance Smith, 1802, 246420 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Framed oval image (damaged) of Constance Smith, 1802, 246419 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Round black medallion - Admiral Nelson's head in relief, 246418 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Black framed engraving of Sir Sidney Smith, 246417 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Copper plate-engraving of Sir Sidney Smith, dated 1796, 246416 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Family crest engraving plate, 246415 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lithograph of Sir Sidney Smith, 1804, 246414 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Oversize watercolors [6], 246413 (Map-drawer 34)